<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[James Smith]]></title>
  <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-29T10:58:37+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://floppy.org.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Smith]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[james@floppy.org.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Energy illiteracy]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/29/energy-illiteracy/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-29T10:23:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/29/energy-illiteracy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier this week more licenses were handed out for oil and gas extraction under the UK, and if you live in the Horsham area, it&rsquo;s very likely that <a href="https://www.og.decc.gov.uk/eng/fox/decc/PED300X/licence?LICENCE_TYPE=PEDL&amp;LICENCE_NO=243">Celtique Energie</a> or <a href="https://www.og.decc.gov.uk/eng/fox/decc/PED300X/licence?LICENCE_TYPE=PEDL&amp;LICENCE_NO=244">Cuadrilla</a> now have a right to extract the resources under your home. Also, the government are currently <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/underground-drilling-access">in the process of changing the law</a> so that you won&rsquo;t have the right to object to this if it happens.</p>

<p>There are many reasons to object to fracking &ndash; some good, some bad &ndash; but the one that concerns me most is that <a href="http://www.economist.com/news/business/21577097-either-governments-are-not-serious-about-climate-change-or-fossil-fuel-firms-are">proven fossil fuels reserves are way higher than the amount we can use</a> while having a chance of staying within a 2 degree rise in global temperatures. We simply can&rsquo;t burn what we already have, so finding more seems a wilfully ignorant course.</p>

<p>Perhaps someone can explain to me why we seem so obsessed with propping up the energy status quo, rather than moving forward? The other day, UKIP councillors in Sussex <a href="http://www.wscountytimes.co.uk/news/letters/letter-petition-to-stop-new-wind-farm-1-6195820">voiced strong objections to the new Rampion wind farm</a> which will be built off the south coast, while at the same time their party welcomes fracking for gas and oil all across the Weald, which would be <em>much</em> more invasive. Having said that though, their climate beliefs are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UKIP#Energy.2C_environment_and_climate_change">absolutely laughable</a>, so we shouldn&rsquo;t be surprised at such anti-scientific, pro-business posturing. How they are considered &ldquo;anti-establishment&rdquo; is beyond me.</p>

<p>It seems to me that the conservative side of British politics is not concerned with conserving our countryside, our society, our future, or anything else, but instead with conserving the ways that they and their friends got their money and power.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d much rather the country followed the model of Balcombe, right here in Horsham constituency. When presented with the threat of fracking, they didn&rsquo;t just say NO (though they did), they then created <a href="http://www.repowerbalcombe.com/our-mission/">Repower Balcombe</a> to provide 100% of their own energy from renewable sources.</p>

<p>This kind of thinking is how we move forward to the future, not by propping up the profits of outdated energy production industries and hedge fund managers for a few more months.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The machine that goes BEEP]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/24/the-machine-that-goes-beep/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-24T07:47:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/24/the-machine-that-goes-beep</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I commute into London a few days a week, and my nearest station is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Littlehaven_railway_station">Littlehaven</a>, a small station on the <a href="http://www.southernrailway.com/">Southern</a> network. Over the last little while, Southern have been introducing an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integrated_Transport_Smartcard_Organisation">ITSO</a> smartcard called <a href="https://www.southernrailway.com/smart-card/">The Key</a>, which is pretty great. Now that I have my season ticket on one, I don&rsquo;t have a scraggly piece of card in my wallet, I feel safer if I lose  it, I can order tickets quickly online, and other good stuff. In general it&rsquo;s a good bit of kit.</p>

<p>However, there&rsquo;s only one problem. At Littlehaven, the card readers are outside, and whenever I tap in and out, they beep <em>really</em> loudly. It&rsquo;s so loud that it must disturb the people in the houses nearby, especially when they&rsquo;re sleeping with their windows open in the current heat. I feel awful every time I tap in and out, I really do.</p>

<p>When putting these in, there was a failure to think about where these machines were going. On a platform in a large station, or inside a station building, no problem, but out in the open near houses is a bad idea. The externalities weren&rsquo;t taken into account.</p>

<p>This has made me think about how we design and deploy technologies in general. In the past, the technology itself was often the driver of its form and function; nowadays we have a lot more user-centred design going on, where technology is designed to meet the precise and simple need that the user has. We need to remember to widen that though, to consider the wider impact our technologies have on the world around us; we need more society-centred design.</p>

<p>Technology is, I believe, a force for good, but we must remember what a powerful driver of social change it is, and that almost any technology choice has inherent assumptions about the society it fits into. When Tim Berners-Lee invented the World Wide Web, it came with a built-in set of assumptions about freedom, democratisation of information, and so on (good ones, in my opinion). When we use Facebook, we&rsquo;re buying into the societal assumption that we are not citizens but products, whose information is handed over to trade to advertisers and others to build shareholder value for Facebook, <em>and that that&rsquo;s OK</em>.</p>

<p>Ethics are important in technology; we need to be aware of what we&rsquo;re building and the wider impact it will have on society at large if it succeeds. We can use technology to build a better society, or we can let it evolve along its own lines without making those choices. Personally, I&rsquo;d rather be in a world of well-designed ethical technology that makes the world better, than surrounded by badly-placed machines that go beep.</p>

<p>In the meantime, I&rsquo;m going to see if I can go back to a paper ticket until they turn down the volume. I don&rsquo;t like waking up the neighbours simply to make my wallet neater.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Answering back]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/22/answering-back/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-22T07:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/22/answering-back</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the archive for other posts.</em></p>

<p>There are a few of common reactions I get from people when I tell them I&rsquo;m standing (though by far the response is positive).</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to put down my own responses to them here. Note that the questions aren&rsquo;t direct quotes from particular individuals, they are a kind of merged version of many times I&rsquo;ve been asked the same thing. I&rsquo;ve tried not to caricature them, but they are simplified; apologies if anyone feels I&rsquo;m putting words into their mouths.</p>

<h2>Why Bother?</h2>

<p><strong>Voting doesn&rsquo;t change anything, so neither will standing. And even if you get in, you&rsquo;ll have no power.</strong></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s a pretty damning indictment of our system, right there. If voters have no power, and even elected representatives have no power, isn&rsquo;t it time to change that? Thing is, these changes take time and effort, and unless you&rsquo;re going to literally start a revolution out on the streets, what other routes do we have other than voting and standing? No seat is safe if people vote for a different option. It won&rsquo;t be easy, but it is possible if we work together. I know that&rsquo;s optimistic, but what&rsquo;s the alternative other than fatalistic disengagement?</p>

<p>In the end, my response to &ldquo;why bother&rdquo; comes down to this. If your ideal roadmap for the future doesn&rsquo;t include people that you agree with in government at some point, then what <em>is</em> your roadmap? Will you be out on the streets in violent revolution, or will you be running the underground in a police state? Or are you waiting for the established wealth and power of our political class to voluntarily change its mind and go in a direction you like?</p>

<h2>We can work around it!</h2>

<p><strong>We can fix this with technology. Encrypt everything, work around government interference, make it impossible for them to spy on us.</strong></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve heard this one a number of times in the surveillance-related conversations I&rsquo;ve been in, and I disagree wholeheartedly. So, encryption is great, and all these privacy-protecting things are wonderful; however, I don&rsquo;t want to live somewhere where it&rsquo;s necessary to use them to protect myself from <em>my own government</em>. I don&rsquo;t want to end up in an encryption arms race against well-funded domestic intelligence agencies, who at the end of the day can come round and arrest me if I&rsquo;m using suspicious anonymous routing software. There <em>are</em> places like this in the world today, and I have no desire to see the UK turning into one of them. It would, quite frankly, be a shitty way to live.</p>

<h2>Why Horsham?</h2>

<p><strong>Horsham&rsquo;s a very safe Tory seat, you&rsquo;ll never win there. Why not stand somewhere else?</strong></p>

<p>This one&rsquo;s easy. I think that the parachuting-in of candidates by central parties is a terrible thing for voter engagement. The idea of candidates working their way up through marginals, then being rewarded with a nice safe seat once they&rsquo;re at the upper end of the party is one of the really bad aspects of our system at the moment. We actually propose in the manifesto that <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk/manifesto/democracy.html#standing-for-election">candidates must live or work in the constituency they want to stand for, and have done so for a while beforehand</a>.</p>

<p>So, because I <em>live</em> in Horsham, that&rsquo;s where I&rsquo;m standing. It&rsquo;s the place I&rsquo;m a part of, that I call home, and that I care about. Is that enough of a reason? Yes, it&rsquo;ll be a hard fight, but what isn&rsquo;t?</p>

<h2>Why Francis?</h2>

<p><strong>Why are you standing against Francis Maude? He&rsquo;s one of the good guys!</strong></p>

<p>This comes along a lot in the Open Data and civic technology worlds. First, I&rsquo;d refer you to my above answer &ndash; I&rsquo;m standing <em>for</em> a better way of doing things, not <em>against</em> Francis in particular.</p>

<p>I quite agree that Francis has done good things during his time in government. His creation of <a href="https://gds.blog.gov.uk/">GDS</a> and the work around <a href="http://gov.uk">gov.uk</a> has been excellent, and I&rsquo;m quite sure that the transformation agenda currently going across the civil service will lead to great things. From what I hear, he&rsquo;s incredibly engaged in these things, and for that I thank him.</p>

<p>Also, his dedication to government transparency is to be lauded (and continued in future). I probably wouldn&rsquo;t have the great job I have now at the <a href="http://theodi.org">ODI</a> if Francis hadn&rsquo;t given his support to the organisation during its formation, so I have that to thank him for as well.</p>

<p>However, and I&rsquo;m being realistic here, if I take Francis&#8217; seat in 2015, then it&rsquo;ll be a sign of a much larger shift in British politics, and it&rsquo;s quite likely that he wouldn&rsquo;t have been in his job any more anyway. The likelihood of the rest of the establishment remaining unchanged, and me just taking out the one good guy in government is <em>very</em> low.</p>

<p>Of course, while he&rsquo;s done good things in the area of online and transparent government, he&rsquo;s been heavily involved in much of the austerity agenda, has made statements about reducing the rights of teachers and others to go on strike, and many other more traditional Tory policies which I don&rsquo;t like.</p>

<p>The government&rsquo;s digital and transparency agendas will continue; we shouldn&rsquo;t get too attached to the person running them.</p>

<h2>Apologies (sort of)</h2>

<p>However, I do feel for those who will probably have to have awkward conversations about why one of their own is running against a key figure in government; if I make your life difficult, I can only apologise.</p>

<p>All I can say is that both my current employment and my choice to stand are a natural parts of my own personal trajectory, and that nobody should see it as some conspiracy of a radical think-tank trying to take over the country. If it was, I imagine they&rsquo;d be rather more effective, anyway. ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Party On]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/14/party-on/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T11:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/14/party-on</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the archive for other posts.</em></p>

<p>Currently, I&rsquo;m intending to stand as an Independent candidate. I believe that candidates should be a lot more independent, and that parties, while useful for some things, tend to wield far too much power.</p>

<p>However, we find ourselves in a political climate that doesn&rsquo;t reward the independent, and doesn&rsquo;t allow lone voices through. Also, there are some built-in biases in the system against the independent candidate.</p>

<p>There has been an open question for a while on the OpenPolitics Manifesto over whether it should form a party. Some think we should, some not. I personally fall on the side that says that forming a party is a good thing, if only for short-term tactical reasons. It would be a party designed to make itself unnecessary by reforming the democratic system. The alternative view is that we would be better as a loose collection of independents.</p>

<p>This post is a long-form contribution to that debate, really.</p>

<p>In my view, the disadvantages of remaining independents mainly come down to brand awareness. When you have to get home a very simple strong message to as many people as possible, being able to present that in a unified way that people will come across in lots of places is a big advantage. Nuanced messages about being an independent but having a shared manifesto will get lost.</p>

<p>Also, the fact that parties get to have their party name, logo, and tagline on the ballot paper is a massive advantage to them over independents, who get none of that.</p>

<p>Anyway, a thought occurred to me. We want to remain a decentralised network of contributors, but capitalise on shared recognition and branding. How can we be a party without being a party? What if we register a party with the Electoral Commission, but avoid the use of the word &ldquo;Party&rdquo; like hell?</p>

<p>Instead, how about the <strong>OpenPolitics Network</strong>?</p>

<p>That way we get the best of both, I think. Anyone could stand as a candidate for the network as long as they are standing on the manifesto, but there&rsquo;s no central party control telling them what to do, or even <em>looking</em> like it does. Each candidate is free to run their campaign however they want; after all, they&rsquo;re basically independents.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the rules state that parties do have to have some centralised aspects &ndash; a leader, and a couple of other posts, but these can be elected from the pool of contributors, and while they may <em>technically</em> exist, we can avoid using them in the usual way.</p>

<p>I think this might be a way to gain the advantages of party recognition without having to conform to the existing views of parties.</p>

<p>Oh, and there is no registered party in the UK at the moment that uses the word &ldquo;network&rdquo;, so I think that&rsquo;s a good omen.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DRIP: An Open Letter to Francis Maude]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/14/drip-an-open-letter-to-francis-maude/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T10:16:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/14/drip-an-open-letter-to-francis-maude</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear Mr Maude,</p>

<p>I am writing to you today as one of your constituents, in relation to the imminent vote on the Data Retention and Investigatory Powers Bill. The government&rsquo;s actions in this area give me great cause for concern.</p>

<p>In April, the EU Data Retention Directive was ruled as a breach of basic citizen rights by the European Courts of Justice. Too much data stored for too long, on too many people. Then, suddenly, last week, the DRIP Bill appears, ready to be pushed through with haste, due to an &ldquo;emergency&rdquo; need to respond to this.</p>

<p>Firstly, what has changed since April? What requires upsetting the normal procedures of review and taking time over legislation? Civic society will not have sufficient time to inspect this legislation and object (though many are trying their best to analyse the text before it becomes law). How is there a sudden &ldquo;emergency&rdquo;?</p>

<p>Secondly, you are a champion of transparency and accountability within government. How does the drafting of legislation in secret, even <em>with</em> cross-party consensus, square with that? Are citizens not to be trusted on matters such as this? I will be interested in seeing your vote on this, to see how far your commitment to transparency goes.</p>

<p>Thirdly, the bill itself gives much cause for concern. The initial claim was that it only reinstates existing powers (which, by the way, were declared illegal), but <a href="http://cyberleagle.blogspot.com/2014/07/dissecting-emergency-data-retention-and.html">analysis is suggesting</a> that it also extends that power to many other areas.</p>

<p>We are a democracy. We are a free country. Secretive extension of the surveillance state, done in haste without oversight, <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/debate/article-2690181/David-Davis-devastating-attack-loss-privacy-This-data-law-catching-terrorists-lust-power.html">has no place here</a>. The government has a responsibility to balance the needs of security services against the freedoms of its citizens, which were hard-won over hundreds of years, and should not be limited lightly.</p>

<p>I announced a couple of weeks ago that <a href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/06/27/standing-for-parliament-in-2015/">I intend to stand for Horsham in next year&rsquo;s general election</a>, on a <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk">collaborative and open-source political platform</a> built by normal citizens.</p>

<p>Horsham is my home, so my choice to stand was not <em>against you</em>, but rather <em>for Horsham</em>. However, with the government&rsquo;s actions over this bill, I am rather looking forward to challenging your choices and true commitment to openness and transparency over the next year.</p>

<p>Note: I have published this letter on my <a href="http://floppy.org.uk">personal website</a>, and will also publish your response to it, to give you proper right of reply.</p>

<p>Yours sincerely,
James Smith</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So what's stopping you?]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/10/so-whats-stopping-you/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-10T09:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/10/so-whats-stopping-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the archive for other posts.</em></p>

<p>Tomorrow it will be 300 days until the General Election. <a href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/06/27/standing-for-parliament-in-2015/">I&rsquo;ve decided to stand</a>, and have been looking into the practicalities of it all (see the blog archive for more articles on this).</p>

<p>In this blog, I want to ask a question. I know that a lot of people out there are politically engaged, and are angry with the choices available to them. I see regular attacks on all the major parties, and a massive distaste for the rise of UKIP. So, the question is this:</p>

<p><em>What&rsquo;s stopping you?</em></p>

<p>Our democracy is far from perfect, but the way I see it, if you&rsquo;re angry with the choices available to you, you only have two options:</p>

<ol>
<li>Take to the streets</li>
<li>Create your own alternative</li>
</ol>


<p>Note that &ldquo;tweet angrily&rdquo; isn&rsquo;t on there, and so unless you&rsquo;re taking option 1 and are going to camp out in Parliament Square in some kind of British Spring, you&rsquo;re left with option 2.</p>

<p>The great thing about our system is that you <em>can</em> create your own option, and the great thing about <em>now</em> is that that option is available to you in just 300 days&#8217; time.</p>

<p>Are you avoiding it because it&rsquo;s too complicated? Well, I have no idea what I&rsquo;m doing, but I&rsquo;m working it all out as I go along in a series of blog posts, so that might help.</p>

<p>Is it because it won&rsquo;t make a difference? In a way, that&rsquo;s not the point. That&rsquo;s like saying you won&rsquo;t vote. The system <em>doesn&rsquo;t work</em> if people don&rsquo;t take part, and yes, most of them will lose, but that&rsquo;s how we decide together.</p>

<p>How about because the major parties have it all sewn up? Well, things are changing. With the web, social media, and other things that the majors don&rsquo;t really get, there is an amazing opportunity for disruption of the status quo. There&rsquo;s a lot of talk about how democracy will change in the future. Well, the future doesn&rsquo;t come unless someone <em>does it</em>, so let&rsquo;s do it.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t know enough? Well, neither do they, I guarantee you; that&rsquo;s why they&rsquo;re surrounded by advisors. Fortunately we have advisors too &ndash; each other.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t know what to actually stand for? There are plenty to pick from that you can join, or you can help the <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk">OpenPolitics Manifesto</a> project, an open-source election manifesto that anyone can edit. Taking part and holding your opinions up for inspection is a great way to refine and improve them, and you <em>won&rsquo;t</em> be simply shot down for saying something stupid; we all do that.</p>

<p>So, what&rsquo;s left? That&rsquo;s it&rsquo;s just too much hard work?</p>

<p>Guess what. Like anything worth fighting for, democracy <em>is</em> hard work, and a long slog, but someone has to do it. However, the more of us do it, the greater support network we will have, and the wider we can spread the load.</p>

<p>Join me on the adventure, and we&rsquo;ll change the world. Maybe not this time, maybe not next, but if the &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; political class is still running the country when we&rsquo;re old and grey, wouldn&rsquo;t that be a wasted opportunity?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diving into election finances]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/08/diving-into-election-finances/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-08T19:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/08/diving-into-election-finances</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the archive for other posts.</em></p>

<p>After talking to the electoral commission yesterday, I got interested in what local candidates normally spend on their campaigns.</p>

<p>Fortunately, this is all open data. The Electoral Commission publish the statistics about election spending on their website, all under the Open Government License. All figures in this article come from them.</p>

<p>There is one particular dataset which we&rsquo;ll dive into here; the <a href="http://www.electoralcommission.org.uk/find-information-by-subject/elections-and-referendums/past-elections-and-referendums/uk-general-elections/candidate-election-spending">candidate spending in the 2010 general election</a>. This lists all candidates in the general election of 2010, what they spent, what they raised, and even better, what the split of spending was. It also includes the number of votes they gained, so you could do some handy analysis of spending vs seats gained, perhaps. There&rsquo;s lots of data in there, so what follows are excerpts, not the whole lot.</p>

<h2>Total spending</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at campaign spending first.</p>

<p>We had 8 candidates in the last election. During the long campaign (see yesterday&rsquo;s post), they were allowed to spend <strong>£30,429.48</strong>. During the short campaign, they were allowed to spend <strong>£12,579.48</strong>.</p>

<table class="table table-striped">
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th> Party </th>
<th> Votes </th>
<th> Long Campaign Spend </th>
<th> Short Campaign Spend</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Conservatives </td>
<td>   29,447 </td>
<td> £3,577.41 </td>
<td> £7,564.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Lib Dems </td>
<td> 17,987 </td>
<td> £1,158.83 </td>
<td> £4,446.94</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Labour Party </td>
<td> 4,189 </td>
<td> £75.75 </td>
<td> £1,460.67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> UKIP </td>
<td> 2,839 </td>
<td> £350.00 </td>
<td> £2,299.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Green Party </td>
<td> 570 </td>
<td> £0.00 </td>
<td> £0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Christian Party </td>
<td> 469 </td>
<td> £0.00 </td>
<td> £1,056.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Peace Party </td>
<td> 253 </td>
<td> £0.00 </td>
<td> £400.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Independent </td>
<td> 87 </td>
<td> £0.00 </td>
<td> £501.09</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><a href="https://plot.ly/~Floppy/1"><img src="http://floppy.org.uk/images/2010_horsham_campaign_spending.png" alt="2010 Horsham Campaign Spending" /></a></p>

<p>So, what can we learn from this?</p>

<ol>
<li><p>The total cost of the campaign was not much over £11k for the highest-spending party. That&rsquo;s reassuring.</p></li>
<li><p>None of them spent anywhere near the maximum allowed.</p></li>
<li><p>Most of the spending happens in the short campaign; this makes sense, as that&rsquo;s when your mailouts happen, etc.</p></li>
<li><p>The Green Party spent <em>nothing</em>. That explains why I never got a leaflet telling me about the candidate. I&rsquo;m going to ignore anyone else who suggests I&rsquo;ll split their vote now, as they quite obviously <em>aren&rsquo;t interested</em> here.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Where does the money go?</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s dig into a bit more detail on what that money is spent on. We&rsquo;ll just look at the Conservatives here, as they have the largest spend.</p>

<table class='table table-striped'>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th> Category </th>
<th> Spend </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Advertising </td>
<td> £966.32 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Leaflets </td>
<td> £4,897.67 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Staff </td>
<td> £4,177.63 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Accommodation </td>
<td> £1,100.48 </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>This is really interesting for my planning. The actual cost of getting a leaflet to (presumably) every home in the constituency (which has 77,000 voters) is <em>under £5k</em>. That&rsquo;s a <em>lot</em> less than I expected, and should totally be crowdfundable. That&rsquo;s verified by the other parties as well &ndash; the Lib Dems spent a similar amount.</p>

<h2>Learning more</h2>

<p>This has given me some really useful insights. I&rsquo;d recommend having a dig into the figures for your area as well, you might find something interesting! I think this could be a good data-driven website as well &ndash; exposing this stuff through a nice data visualisation would be lovely; maybe a project for <a href="http://twitter.com/democlub">Democracy Club</a>?</p>

<p>You can dig into the data at the link above, and <a href="http://www.electoralcommission.org.uk/__data/assets/pdf_file/0011/163793/EPE-Part-3-Spending-and-donations-for-individual-candidates.pdf">this guide</a> from the Electoral Commission gives lots more detail on what it all means. It&rsquo;s for the 2014 EU elections, but the concepts are the same, so it&rsquo;s a decent reference. I&rsquo;ll be digging more into that guide as I go along, sorting out my own finances, so more of this to come.</p>

<p>Until next time&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning from the Electoral Commission]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/07/learning-from-the-electoral-commission/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-07T16:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/07/learning-from-the-electoral-commission</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the archive for other posts.</em></p>

<p>So, today I spoke to the Electoral Commission. In my last post, I made a bunch of assumptions based on reading their website about what was legal and what wasn&rsquo;t. Today I checked all that with them, and was pretty much right, thankfully.</p>

<p>The Commission offices all have their <a href="http://www.electoralcommission.org.uk/contact-us/our-offices">phone numbers online</a>, and connect you straight to people who can answer your questions. I highly recommend giving them a call if you&rsquo;re considering this yourself.</p>

<p>So, what did we find out? (By the way &ndash; don&rsquo;t take this as solid legal advice, it&rsquo;s just my own interpretation, not guaranteed fact)</p>

<h2>Standing</h2>

<p>There aren&rsquo;t many rules around actually standing. First of all, it&rsquo;s perfectly legal to announce that you intend to, as I have. You don&rsquo;t have to have anything &ldquo;official&rdquo; in place first.</p>

<p>The regulated campaigning period doesn&rsquo;t start until mid-December, so until then, you can do what you like. After that, things become a little more regulated financially, but more of that later.</p>

<p>As for registering as a candidate, or as a party, that all comes a lot later. The deadlines will be a few weeks before the election itself, so the official signing of things can be put off for a good while yet. Parties can be registered until a little while before the actual candidate nomination deadline, so we&rsquo;ve got plenty of time to decide if this gets branded with a party name or not.</p>

<h2>Spending</h2>

<p>There was a bit more around finances, but again this only takes effect during the regulated period. There is a period starting in mid-December called the &ldquo;Long Campaign&rdquo;, which changes to the &ldquo;Short Campaign&rdquo; nearer the actual election date. Each period has different spending limits, but I&rsquo;m not worrying about that too much yet.</p>

<p>You need to report all spending on the campaign to the Commission, but it&rsquo;s just a matter of keeping simple books of expenditure. No rocket science here, and in my case I&rsquo;m going to have it all open anyway. Again, this doesn&rsquo;t take effect until the start of the Long Campaign, but I&rsquo;ll probably start now anyway.</p>

<p>Incidentally, if you start campaigning early, but don&rsquo;t officially register until later, the need to keep the books applies retroactively, so just get ahead and make sure you keep track from the beginning.</p>

<h2>Raising money</h2>

<p>This was the interesting bit.</p>

<p>You can raise money to spend during your campaign any way you like, but you must disclose who your donors are. For independent candidates, all donations over £50 must be disclosed &ndash; the figure for parties is higher, I think.</p>

<p>The interesting part is that all donors must be on the electoral roll, and <em>you</em> have to verify this. This makes crowdfunding interesting. Apparently some people have tried it, but found it very hard to get the right information to check that their donors are legal. I&rsquo;m hoping to start a conversation with crowdfunding organisations <em>now</em> to try to get this sorted out so I can do things that way.</p>

<p>To summarise, so far, the legalities around standing for election are pretty minimal. Just a bit of bookkeeping, and making sure your money comes from the right places. Should be even easier with the kind of radically transparent approach I&rsquo;ll be taking.</p>

<p>On to the next step!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Work In Progress]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/06/30/work-in-progress/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-30T16:35:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/06/30/work-in-progress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the archive for other posts.</em></p>

<p>A few days ago, I announced that <a href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/06/27/standing-for-parliament-in-2015">I intend to stand for Parliament next May</a>. Since then, I&rsquo;ve had a bunch of really great feedback (thank you all!), suggestions, and questions. Lots of questions have been about the process of standing, and about how complex it is.</p>

<p>The entertaining thing is that I&rsquo;ve had to answer most these with an &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t know&rdquo;, as I really don&rsquo;t at this stage. Really all I&rsquo;ve got so far is an intent, a lack of self-control, and am comfortable with the fact that <a href="http://codon.com/i-have-no-idea-what-im-doing">I have no idea what I&rsquo;m doing</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://i3.kym-cdn.com/photos/images/newsfeed/000/234/739/fa5.jpg" alt="I have no idea what I'm doing" /></p>

<p>However, my campaign is all about openness, so I&rsquo;m going to blog the whole thing as I go along and learn what&rsquo;s what. Watch this space, and I&rsquo;ll walk you through the entire process, and maybe remove some of the fear so that you can do it too. I&rsquo;ll also try to distill the knowledge into a guide of some sort as I go along &ndash; more on that later.</p>

<p>Here goes, anyway. Here&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s happened up until now.</p>

<h2>Making the decision</h2>

<p>Step one in all this is perhaps the biggest. However, all you need is a desire to make the world better, to have the realisation that democracy needs people to stand up for what they believe in, and that if nobody else will do it, you&rsquo;d better take it on yourself.</p>

<p>You should have some idea what you want to stand for at this point, but I don&rsquo;t think it has to be final and polished. The joy of the <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk">OpenPolitics Manifesto</a> is that it will keep being refined and improved right up until the election (and beyond). It&rsquo;s essential to expose your ideas to some criticism and discussion though; it&rsquo;s a great way to refine them, and they <em>will</em> be challenged later.</p>

<p>A few people have asked why I&rsquo;m standing in Horsham, which will be a hard fight. Honestly, it never occurred to stand anywhere other than where I live &ndash; why would anyone vote for me if I have no connection with the area? The parachuting-in of candidates is one broken aspect of our system if you ask me. Anyway&hellip;</p>

<h2>Talking about it</h2>

<p>The first person I discussed it with was, of course, my wife Amanda, who would probably much rather I kept to myself, but knows me too well to expect me to. If this is something you&rsquo;re going to do, you&rsquo;ve got to have your family on board. I&rsquo;ve made a promise to her that I&rsquo;ll try to keep the time spent under control, and if this starts to have an effect on the time I spend with my children, then I&rsquo;ll stop. They come first. Obviously this will be hardest in the immediate run-up to the election, but it&rsquo;s the right aim to have.</p>

<p>Once she was on board, I told my bosses at the <a href="http://theodi.org">ODI</a>, and a few close friends with interests in the area. All the feedback was very positive, which was really great. Your extended networks will be a massive source of power and support, and far from getting the expected &ldquo;why the hell would you do that&rdquo; response, I&rsquo;ve had a massive outpouring of support, respect, and admiration for doing it. Win.</p>

<h2>Checking the law</h2>

<p>So, time to tell the world.</p>

<p>Hmm; perhaps I&rsquo;d better check it&rsquo;s legal first.</p>

<p>I spent a bit of time looking at the <a href="http://electoralcommission.org.uk">Electoral Commission</a> website, which looks nice but leads you in circles a bit, and doesn&rsquo;t currently have guidance for people standing in UK parliamentary elections in 2015. Obviously I&rsquo;m a bit ahead of the game here.</p>

<p>Cobbling together information from byelection guidance, and other sources,  it seems fairly simple. There are spending limits on election campaigning while you&rsquo;re a candidate, and some other rules, but the <a href="http://www.electoralcommission.org.uk/__data/assets/pdf_file/0004/162724/reg-period-timeline-candidate.pdf">actual time you are an official candidate is quite short</a>. There is something about a &ldquo;long campaign&rdquo; and a &ldquo;short campaign&rdquo; in there, but the rules only seem to apply once certain dates are passed. The long campaign starts in mid-December, so I&rsquo;m basically ignoring it for now. As far as I can tell, that&rsquo;s the only point that accounts and things have to be kept, though I am going to start keeping track of costs etc. now (in public of course).</p>

<p>So, there&rsquo;s nothing stopping you announcing an intention. When it comes to actually registering, you have to submit nomination papers with 10 signatures from your constituency, and a £500 deposit. The deadline is really quite close to the election itself though, so that&rsquo;s a long way off.</p>

<p>You get your deposit back if you gain 5% of the votes cast; in Horsham I think that&rsquo;s about 2800 based on the numbers at the last election. I intend to find a way to crowdfund that deposit, btw; not because I can&rsquo;t afford it, but to show others who can&rsquo;t that it&rsquo;s not a barrier to participation.</p>

<h2>Time to announce</h2>

<p>So, I think it&rsquo;s legal to do what I&rsquo;m trying to do. I love working in the open, so I guess it&rsquo;s time to tell people! I wrote a blog post, but then realised that people might want to express an interest, so cobbled together a landing page at <a href="http://openhorsham.org.uk">openhorsham.org.uk</a>.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a <a href="http://mailchimp.com">mailchimp</a> mailing list, and a <a href="http://facebook.com/openhorsham">Facebook</a> page; both were easy to set up, and I should be fine on the free mailchimp plan for a long time. Both will let me get in touch with people who are interested in spreading the word. I&rsquo;m also trying out <a href="http://gosquared.com">GoSquared</a> to count website visitors &ndash; they promise not to share visitor data with others, so it&rsquo;s privacy-friendly.</p>

<p>Incidentally, I chose a Facebook page rather than a group. Facebook doesn&rsquo;t make it massively clear which is appropriate for what, but as this is a contact point for a <em>thing</em>, a page seemed more sensible.</p>

<p>Once that was up, I just needed to wait for the perfect time to launch&hellip;</p>

<p>Actually, no. There&rsquo;s no perfect time. I managed to wait about 10 minutes before I got so itchy about it that I had to just go ahead and publish.</p>

<p>The post went up here and on <a href="http://medium.com">medium</a>. I chose medium because there&rsquo;s no barrier to writing there, but I <em>think</em> people are more inclined to share their links than links to this site.</p>

<h2>What didn&rsquo;t I do?</h2>

<p>Because I did so little before announcing, there&rsquo;s a <em>lot</em> I haven&rsquo;t done, but these are the big things that you might think you need first:</p>

<ul>
<li>I didn&rsquo;t assemble a team of helpers. That can come later, and they will choose themselves.</li>
<li>I didn&rsquo;t change my twitter handle (<a href="http://twitter.com/Floppy">@Floppy</a>) &ndash; I am who I am, I&rsquo;m not going to polish my public image.</li>
<li>I didn&rsquo;t chase the media. I thought for a while that I had to, but was reminded that it wasn&rsquo;t my style, so would be the wrong thing to do. They will come to me if they&rsquo;re interested enough.</li>
<li>I didn&rsquo;t agonise over a name for the campaign. I&rsquo;ve used Open Horsham for now, but that can change later &ndash; it&rsquo;s a work in progress.</li>
</ul>


<h2>What&rsquo;s happened since?</h2>

<p>Well, today I had my first conversation with a local journalist, so that strategy worked.</p>

<p>Next steps are to get the message spread further (especially locally), and probably organise a get-together in a Horsham pub. I also need to get more content down in the manifesto and attract more contributors there. I&rsquo;ve also got to work out how far I can push the transparency &ndash; can I stream (or at least record and publish later) all the meetings and things I have with people, all the discussions? Someone suggested recording a making-of documentary as I go along. Anyone got a camera and a lot of free time?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m very much taking a &ldquo;push it and see what breaks&rdquo; approach to this project, but it&rsquo;s always served me well in the past, so we&rsquo;ll see what happens this time!</p>

<p>Tune in next time to find out what happens when I phone up the South-East Electoral Commission team and see if my assumptions are actually right&hellip; :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Standing for Parliament in 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/06/27/standing-for-parliament-in-2015/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-27T10:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/06/27/standing-for-parliament-in-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the archive for other posts.</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve got an exciting announcement to make; <strong>in May 2015, I&rsquo;m planning to stand in the
general election to be MP for Horsham</strong>. I&rsquo;ll be running on the
principles in the <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk">OpenPolitics Manifesto</a>,
an open source collaborative manifesto that <em>anyone</em> can contribute to; I&rsquo;m reasonably sure that&rsquo;s a world first.</p>

<h2>Why do this?</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m an optimist. I look to the future and hope that we can build a brighter, happier, more collaborative, more equal society for everyone, enabled by the best aspects of our technology. I see a future where we can do <em>democracy itself</em> better, where we all have a say in the way we do things together. I realise that&rsquo;s utopian, but I figure that it&rsquo;s better to have a idea of where you want to get to than just stumbling from crisis to crisis without an end goal in mind.</p>

<p>On the other hand, I&rsquo;ve come to the conclusion over the last few years that nobody is
representing me or others who are optimistically working towards a better future. I&rsquo;m fed up of the politics of fear, the <a href="https://therearenoothers.wordpress.com/2011/12/28/othering-101-what-is-othering/">othering</a> of the vulnerable, and the misguided doctrine of austerity. I&rsquo;m also frustrated by our lack of sufficient climate action, and our dismal record when adopting supposedly &ldquo;new&rdquo; technologies like the web. The bleak future offered by the current political choices just isn&rsquo;t a place I want to be.</p>

<p>So, I think we can do better, and the right way to deal with that in our current system is <em>provide the option yourself</em> and stand for office.</p>

<h2>Starting something</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m the first to admit that it will be a hard fight; I&rsquo;m standing in a very safe Conservative seat, against Francis Maude, a cabinet minister. However, Horsham is where I live, and so while there are probably easier targets, this one falls to me, and I&rsquo;m ready to take it on.</p>

<p>Also, this isn&rsquo;t simply about winning one seat next May; it&rsquo;s about trying to inspire others to stand across the country on the same platform, and about getting started on the long haul of building a political movement across many years and multiple elections. There is a growing movement towards a more networked citizen-powered form of democracy across the world, and standing on an open-source manifesto is an exciting way to be part of that.</p>

<h2>Let&rsquo;s do it</h2>

<p>In summary; I&rsquo;m not a politician, but I <em>do</em> think things need to change if we&rsquo;re going to build a decent future. If you agree, and like me you can&rsquo;t trust anyone else to fix things for you, stand where <em>you</em> are, and maybe we&rsquo;ll put a party name on this thing.</p>

<p><strong>Let&rsquo;s bring an Open Revolution to British politics.</strong></p>

<p><em>If you&rsquo;re in the Horsham area, visit <a href="http://openhorsham.org.uk">openhorsham.org.uk</a> to keep in touch with the campaign when it starts.</em></p>

<p><em>To get involved in writing the manifesto, visit <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk">openpolitics.org.uk</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/OpenPoliticsUK">@OpenPoliticsUK</a> on Twitter.</em></p>

<p><em>And finally, you can follow me on Twitter at <a href="http://twitter.com/Floppy">@Floppy</a>. If you want to stand where you are, let me know!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Open Democracy Stack]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/01/25/the-open-democracy-stack/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-25T08:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/01/25/the-open-democracy-stack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I wrote my blog post <a href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/07/05/its-time-to-step-up/">&ldquo;It&rsquo;s time to step up&rdquo;</a> last summer, I&rsquo;ve got very interested in the concept of Open Democracy, and have been discovering a lot about what&rsquo;s currently going on in this area. This post is an attempt to delineate the various efforts, mainly for my own benefit, but perhaps others may find it useful as well.</p>

<p>There are a number of overlapping concepts. First, we have political parties, with their manifestos. Then we have the idea of a constitution, and finally the policy-making process itself. A few examples:</p>

<h2>Party Manifestos</h2>

<p>Firstly, and most familiar, we have the political party manifesto. My view is that this is a collection of statements that outlines the beliefs of the party, and how it intends to attack problems. It isn&rsquo;t necessarily detailed, or fully costed, but is indicative of the direction that the party wishes to go. The Pirate Party UK will soon be launching their next open manifesto process, and I&rsquo;m experimenting with building a new political platform under the <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk/manifesto">OpenPolitics Manifesto</a> project (an interesting aspect of which is that is designed to deprecate the party system).</p>

<h2>Constitutions</h2>

<p>Then, we have the idea of a constitution. The UK does not have a proper written constitution, but there is a crowdsourcing effort going on at <a href="http://www.constitutionuk.com/">Constitution UK</a> to create one. Interestingly, a lot of ideas that are going into that are ones that I consider far too specific for a constitution, and instead belong in a party manifesto. A consititution should be short, simple, and consist of the basic rules on which we all agree. The constitution can be added to, but it&rsquo;s best to start with something very simple.</p>

<p>Some examples; the structure of Parliament, the role (or lack thereof) of the monarchy, and the <a href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/udhr/">UDHR</a> would belong in a constitution, but things like economic and social policy, including the role of the NHS and welfare state, would not.</p>

<h2>Tenuous Analogies</h2>

<p>To use a computer analogy, if a party manifesto can be considered a piece of software, which the user can choose to run or not, a consitution is more like the OS; a lower-level design that allows the higher-level manifesto to run, and on which all participants in the system agree.</p>

<p>(Obviously, there are many OSes. And we have many countries with different constitutions, so I&rsquo;m sticking with this analogy for now&hellip; let&rsquo;s see where it breaks)</p>

<h2>Open Policy</h2>

<p>Then we have the policy-design level, which is I think what the <a href="http://my.civilservice.gov.uk/policy/">Cabinet Office Open Policy Team</a> is looking at. This is apolitical, driven by the choices made by the electorate, and is about effective implementation of the ideas in a manifesto. In my mind this is like the content that you create using a piece of software. So, it reflects the manifesto commitment used to drive it, but then is richer in terms of how that commitment is implemented, funded, and so on.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The world of Open Democeacy is one with many pieces, and how they all fit together isn&rsquo;t necessarily obvious at the first look. Anyone who wants to contribute to this (including myself) should understand the &lsquo;stack&rsquo; to know which ideas fit where.</p>

<p>And of course, all this could be wrong, it&rsquo;s just my assessment of it. If anyone wants to enlighten me further, please do, and please contribute to all the open democracy efforts that are out there, at whatever level you feel is most appropriate for you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Depression Is A Bug, Not A Feature]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/10/10/depression-is-a-bug-not-a-feature/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-10T11:02:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/10/10/depression-is-a-bug-not-a-feature</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is apparently <a href="http://www.mentalhealth.org.uk/our-work/world-mental-health-day/">World Mental Health Day</a>, which makes it an appropriate time to talk a little about depression. I was thinking of doing this anyway, but today seems a good day to do it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve suffered from intermittent depression for the last few years. If I&rsquo;ve been quiet on Twitter or GitHub for the last couple of weeks, it&rsquo;s because I&rsquo;m currently recovering from my fourth round; they seem to come on just under every two years, it seems. It&rsquo;s not a pleasant thing to admit to, but I honestly believe that only by talking about our experiences can we normalise this, and when you&rsquo;re in the grip of depression, what you really need is to know that you are <em>not alone</em>.</p>

<p>The first time round, I didn&rsquo;t really understand what was happening. Work was stressful, but not ridiculously so, but I lost the ability to cope with it. I couldn&rsquo;t make decisions, and I remember times when I would have to run away and actually <em>hide in a darkened room</em> for a while when something tricky came up like, I dunno, triaging the Monday morning bug list. Fortunately I worked for a flight simulation company at the time, so dark rooms were in plentiful supply.</p>

<p>Depression, for someone who works entirely in their mind, as we do as creative programmers, is utterly debilitating. Imagine:</p>

<ul>
<li>Your mind slows down</li>
<li>You lose the ability to focus, or think straight about problems</li>
<li>You lose the ability to make decisions; even deciding on lunch can be impossible</li>
<li>You lose confidence; feel like you&rsquo;re a fraud, and that you&rsquo;ll be found out</li>
<li>You lose the big picture; you can&rsquo;t hold it all in your head</li>
<li>Anxiety builds, and eventually you find yourself hiding in darkened rooms trying not to panic (and often failing)</li>
</ul>


<p>Our jobs depend on those exact qualities, and often, for many of us, so does our self-worth. I try to compare it to being a sportsman and having a broken leg; it&rsquo;s take you out of the game just as surely, and it robs you of your reason for being just as much.</p>

<p>However; it is manageable. I&rsquo;m still learning, but I am getting better at it. I&rsquo;m spotting it earlier each time, am getting better at warning my co-workers, and have no qualms now with going to the doctor and getting the help I need once it becomes clear. I&rsquo;ve had <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citalopram">medication</a> the last three times; I&rsquo;m currently a week and a half in to this round.</p>

<p>The important thing to realise that <em>it&rsquo;s not a failing, it&rsquo;s an illness</em>. Your brain is a big bag of chemicals that govern your emotions; there&rsquo;s no magical soul hiding there, I&rsquo;m afraid. But sometimes those chemicals go wrong. In the case of depression, it&rsquo;s apparently a long-term reduction in the amount of Serotonin in the brain that does it. Your synapses hoover up too much, so there&rsquo;s not enough left in the gaps to conduct the signals effectively. It can be brought on by stress, by exhaustion, by sudden shocks, or even by a more &lsquo;normal&rsquo; illness. The brain gets out of kilter, and then just gets <em>stuck</em> in this cycle.</p>

<p>But, as an engineer, <em>I can relate to this</em>. Depression is a <em>bug</em>, not a failure on <em>my</em> part. The medication prevents this serotonin reuptake, and lets your brain recover, and remember how to balance itself. I&rsquo;ve proved this to myself time and again; a few days into the medication, I&rsquo;m <em>back</em>. I&rsquo;m me again. For example, I couldn&rsquo;t have written this two days ago, but today I&rsquo;m feeling more&hellip; <em>present</em>. I&rsquo;m not there yet, but it won&rsquo;t be long now.</p>

<p>The people around you have a huge part to play. You need their understanding, support, and for them to give you time to recover. I wouldn&rsquo;t have been able to cope with this if not for my family, my colleagues at <a href="http://amee.com">AMEE</a> and the <a href="http://www.theodi.org">ODI</a>, and for a great friend of mine who, many years ago, taught me how depression works <em>before</em> I found out for myself.</p>

<p>There are a few links I&rsquo;d recommend reading about this:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://revdancatt.com/2012/07/26/leaving-the-guardian-creativity-vs-mild-depression-the-quantified-self-and-running/">Leaving the Guardian, Creativity vs Mild Depression</a> by Rev Dan Catt</li>
<li><a href="http://hyperboleandahalf.blogspot.co.uk/2011/10/adventures-in-depression.html">Adventures in Depression</a> and <a href="http://hyperboleandahalf.blogspot.co.uk/2013/05/depression-part-two.html">Part 2</a> by Hyperbole and a Half</li>
</ul>


<p>That was a bit long, but the TL;DR is this: If you&rsquo;re feeling the symptoms above, then talk to your doctor and <em>get help</em>. It&rsquo;s just a bug, it&rsquo;s fixable, and you are <em>not</em> a failure. If you know someone who seems to be suffering, then try to help them understand what&rsquo;s happening, don&rsquo;t just tell them to &ldquo;cheer up&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It's Time To Step Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/07/05/its-time-to-step-up/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-05T20:08:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/07/05/its-time-to-step-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I find the current state of politics in the UK incredibly depressing.</p>

<p>Unsurprisingly, I find myself disagreeing with most of what the Conservative party is doing in government, and in particular with the narrative they are using to justify it. The Liberal Democrats may claim they have moderated the worst excesses of the Conservatives, but have still allowed the near-privatisation of the NHS, and failed utterly to do anything with the concessions they got in the coalition agreement on things like electoral reform.</p>

<p>On the opposition side&hellip; well, what opposition? I personally like Ed, but it&rsquo;s obvious the media have their teeth into him and will never let him have a proper voice. Worst of all, the Labour Party are buying into the aforementioned narrative of &ldquo;this is what needs to be done&rdquo;. They don&rsquo;t challenge the demonisation of the poor, while entrenched power runs off with the money that&rsquo;s being stripped from our welfare state.</p>

<p>Protest votes are heading to the charismatic far right, with the Old Tory caricatures that are UKIP grabbing all the headlines and dragging the entire country down a path that we <em>really</em> shouldn&rsquo;t be considering. The other minor parties are next to useless. The Greens, really the party I agree with most, will always be mired in 1970&rsquo;s style environmentalism, which nobody will ever vote for en masse.</p>

<p>All this adds up to an uncomfortable truth. Nobody in the public sphere in this country is speaking for <em>me</em>. The narrative is about how the past was better, and the present is broken. The people in power seem to lust after the old days of empire, rather than working out how to take us into a bright shiny future.</p>

<p>The problem is; the future isn&rsquo;t stopping. It will change <em>every single institution we have</em>, and we should be getting excited about that fact and making sure it works <em>for</em> us. That&rsquo;s what I dedicate my life to, to making sure the future is a <em>better</em> place for <em>everyone</em>, but nobody in power seems to want to take us there.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2009/11/10/the-activist-geek-philosophy">written before</a> about a kind of shared philosophy amongst the open society community, but I stopped short of some of the more controversial areas of politics. I think it&rsquo;s time for us to stop doing that. There is an unspoken tradition in our community of trying to be beyond political statements, to fix things from the outside, but the way GDS are reforming the civil service (which I <em>will</em> give the Conservatives credit for, or at least <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Maude">some of them</a>) has reminded me that in order to truly change the system, you sometimes have to <em>become</em> the system.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a general election coming in a couple of years. Those of us who are looking to the future should have our hands in the game. It&rsquo;s time for our community to grow up, take responsibility, and stop leaving the debate to the relics. We have the tools and the skills to do this, and a lot of allies. We&rsquo;re already changing the world from behind the scenes; it&rsquo;s time to start leading from the front as well.</p>

<p>If someone is already doing something about this, I want to know who. If not, we should get started by setting up a GitHub repository, and get collaborating on policy for a brighter future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Mentoring Journey]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/06/04/my-mentoring-journey/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-04T20:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/06/04/my-mentoring-journey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since January, I&rsquo;ve worked at the <a href="http://www.theodi.org">Open Data Institute</a>, which has been a really great experience. As well as being a non-profit with a mission to make the world better, which is already a huge win as far as I&rsquo;m concerned, the organisation also puts a massive emphasis on culture and people. For a small enterprise (less than 20 people), this is amazing, and I&rsquo;ve never seen anything quite like it anywhere I&rsquo;ve worked.</p>

<p>One major part of the culture is the approach to mentoring. Not content with just professional training, the ODI wants all employees to have access to a mentor outside the company, to help develop people in ways that <em>they</em> need, not necessarily in ways that obviously benefit the organisation.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve always felt that I drifted through my professional life in a kind of random walk, without much of a plan. Admittedly, working at the ODI brings together so much of what I&rsquo;ve done over the years that it might <em>look</em> intentional, but it&rsquo;s really just another convenient accident. However, at 37, perhaps it&rsquo;s time to start trying to steer a little. Maybe it&rsquo;s time to get an answer to the classic interview question &ldquo;where do you see yourself in five years&#8217; time?&rdquo;. Because the ODI is about building a movement, a community, it&rsquo;s OK if the answer to the question is &ldquo;not here&rdquo;. People leaving the ODI and starting their own businesses is a Good Thing in a way it wouldn&rsquo;t be anywhere else.</p>

<p>So, where do I want to be? Well, barring career discontinuities, I reckon I should be CTOing somewhere that&rsquo;s making a difference to the things I care about, somewhere in the openness, transparency, democracy, environmental impact sort of area, rather than day-to-day hacking. Maybe that&rsquo;s still the ODI, but if so I should look to be doing more of the strategic stuff by then.</p>

<p>Problem is, I don&rsquo;t know what&rsquo;s missing in order for me to get there. Technically, I can do anything I can turn my hand to, but I know there are deeper mysteries that I know nothing about, but that are important in the wider context of a CTO type role.</p>

<p>The mentoring program is a perfect framework to start thinking about this. I&rsquo;ve been lucky enough find a mentor who has gone through the transition from pure hacker to something a bit more strategic in the shape of <a href="http://flourish.org">Francis Irving</a>, ex of <a href="http://mysociety.org">MySociety</a> and now CEO of <a href="http://scraperwiki.com">ScraperWiki</a>. We share many of our ideals, and I hope I can learn a lot from someone who is a little further down the path than me.</p>

<p>Neither of us really know how this process will work, but we&rsquo;re starting with a bit of set reading (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Innovator's_Dilemma">The Innovator&rsquo;s Dilemma</a> by Clayton M. Christensen) and seeing how it evolves. As we go along, I&rsquo;m going to try to share my thoughts and learning in public, partly as a way of marshalling my own thoughts, and partly as a way to pay Francis&#8217; generosity forward to others.</p>

<p>It will be an adventure, and hopefully I will come out of it with a better understanding both of myself, and my role in the better future I hope to build.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ActiveRecord-style array filtering in Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/08/01/activerecord-style-array-filtering-in-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/08/01/activerecord-style-array-filtering-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rails&#8217; named scopes are fantastic for making readable code with efficient SQL behind the scenes. Given a Person model, you could define a scope called &#8216;adult&#8217; which could add an SQL <em>WHERE</em> for <em>age&gt;18</em>, and let you write pretty code like Person.adult to find all adults. Great! Chaining them together gets even better with code like Person.adult.male.with_glasses.</p>
<p>The problem comes if you do this in a single action with lots of different chained scopes to show different data. You end up with a whole bunch of SQL queries, which can get expensive. In the system I&#8217;m currently building, which includes geospatial queries, this gets far too slow to use. So, instead, let&#8217;s get one big list of objects and filter them in Ruby when we need them.</p>
<p>Simple enough. The only thing is, the ActiveRecord chaining syntax is lovely. I don&#8217;t want to write tons of chained selects with blocks and all that faff. Instead, let&#8217;s extend Array to give us the syntax we like. The trick is to wrap an Array inside another class and then use method_missing to delegate. We then make sure that returned objects aren&#8217;t Arrays, but our new type instead.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s best explained with the code:</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/Floppy/3228297.js"></script>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Therm]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/07/24/introducing-therm/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/07/24/introducing-therm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
<a href="http://www.therm.uk.com"><img src="http://floppy.org.uk/images/therm.png"/></a>
</p>
<p>
It’s been an interesting year. Until April I worked at AMEE as their Platform
Evangelist. I’d been there almost four years, through lots of interesting times.
I got to do cool things like build AskAMEE, hack carbon emissions into Minecraft
(and get on BoingBoing with it), and run the London Green Hackathon. It was sad
when my time there came to an end, but in startup life there is always a point at
which it makes sense to move on.
</p>
<p>
Since then, I’ve been trying to find ways to carry making software that at least
tries to deal with the impending climate crisis that’s heading our way. As I discussed
at the beginning of the year, we don’t have long. I’ve been carrying on building
the Cleanweb UK community that we tried to bootstrap at AMEE on a voluntary basis.
London seems to have the most interesting cleanweb community in the world - we’ve
certainly been doing it longer than anyone else, so we have to capitalise on that
and work together!
</p>
<p>
However, the time has come for me to try and make a living out of this stuff again,
and I’m having a go at doing it by myself.
</p>
<p>
So, meet <a href="http://www.therm.uk.com">Therm</a>. It’s the first specialist cleanweb consultancy in the world (as
far as I know). If you’re doing anything on the web to do with sustainability, Therm
can help - get in touch!
</p>
<p>
It’s just me for now, but maybe later it won’t be. It’ll be an adventure, whatever
happens.
</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Green Is Useless To Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/05/23/green-is-useless-to-me/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/05/23/green-is-useless-to-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I started reading <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/The-Geek-Manifesto-ebook/dp/B007T99H6S" title="The Geek Manifesto">The Geek Manifesto</a>, by Mark Henderson, and, given my particular interests, I started near the end with the chapter on <em>Geeks and Greens</em> before starting properly at the beginning.</p>
<p>I strongly suggest reading it, but to summarise, the traditional green movement is generally unscientific and deeply political, and this has led to counterproductive politicisation and scepticism of scientific issues like climate change.</p>
<p>The greens latched onto a few things correctly by accident, like climate change research, but are still vastly wrong on many others. They come with too much junk science to be credible, and this leaks into the real science that they accidentally picked up. The association of the Green Party, for instance, with homeopathy and other alternative medicine approaches, is just sad in this day and age (although I believe it changed recently, it wouldn&#8217;t surprise me if the party still includes many who do believe this junk).</p>
<p>Add to that that many traditional greens have far-left politics which puts a lot of people off, and you end up with the conclusion that they *cannot* be trusted to be the main voice on important matters of science like climate change, which should essentially be an apolitical issue.</p>
<p>Whether it&#8217;s NGOs like Greenpeace or Friends of the Earth, or political parties like the Green Party here in the UK, they are just too embedded in their history to be able to deal with this properly. They can&#8217;t give up their hatred of nuclear power, for instance, or their opposition to GM science, both of which are probably going to be essential tools for our future, without alienating their core membership.</p>
<p>I agree with Mark that a new approach is needed, but I don&#8217;t think those organisations can be rescued &#8216;from the inside&#8217; as he suggests. They can carry on if they like, but even in the unlikely event that they change their views, the public&#8217;s perception of them would still be the same. We need something new, something reality-based, something that aims to have the clean high-tech future that I <em>personally</em> want.</p>
<p>Even the word &#8216;green&#8217; is now rendered useless by these viewpoints, so we have to just drop it and talk about &#8216;sustainability&#8217; and &#8216;clean&#8217; instead. If someone could come up with a catchy name for it that&#8217;s half as good as &#8216;green&#8217; though, that would be lovely.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Planet Hopper]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/05/15/planet-hopper/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/05/15/planet-hopper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of weeks ago, I went along to ISIC in Harwell to take part in the <a href="http://spaceappschallenge.org/">International Space Apps Challenge</a>, run by NASA. Hackdays are always fun, but this one was particularly exciting, because, you know, SPACE!</p>
<p>At first I thought about doing something with Earth observation data and climate change, but decided I&#8217;d give myself a break from that and do something else for once. After the usual shenanigans forming a team, a few of us started working on something to do with exoplanet data, particularly from the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kepler_(spacecraft)" title="Kepler">Kepler satellite</a>.</p>
<p>We know about tons of planets now, but most people don&#8217;t know much about them. We decided to make something a bit fun and a bit educational. My sister is a physics teacher, so we aimed at creating something she could use in class to stimulate questions from the kids.</p>
<p>The result is <a href="http://www.planethopper.co.uk" title="Planet Hopper">Planet Hopper</a>, a webapp that allows you to explore the exoplanets and see various interesting facts about them in a friendly way. For instance, we tell you how old you would be on the planet, hoping to stimulate the question &#8216;why?&#8217;</p>
<p>We ended up winning the best hack prize at the Harwell site, and are currently in the global judging round, which is always nice.</p>
<p>Technically, this was my first experience with Django. In general, my first assessment was that it seemed perfectly capable, but not as slick as the Rails toolset perhaps. I&#8217;ll keep playing with it though, it&#8217;s always good to know more!</p>
<p>If you want to improve Planet Hopper, you can do; the code is, as always, <a href="http://github.com/Floppy/kepler-explorer" title="Code">on github</a>.</p>
<p><strong>UPDATE</strong>: We won in the global judging! <a href="http://spaceappschallenge.org/blog/2012/05/18/global-winners-announced/">&#8220;Most Inspiring&#8221;</a> - pretty sweet! </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The need for Cleanweb R&D]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/03/12/the-need-for-cleanweb-rd/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/03/12/the-need-for-cleanweb-rd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The newly-named cleanweb is a strange place. It&#8217;s all about social change, better sustainability, and other such noble goals, but it&#8217;s shackled by the demands of today&#8217;s economy; people with mortgages need proper jobs and investors need returns. The potential is enormous, but the opportunity to really explore it feels tiny. Some companies (like <a href="http://www.amee.com">AMEE</a>) do explore this space, but are still bound to go with the most commercially-viable opportunities. There&#8217;s very little space for blue-sky thinking.</p>
<p>I have a gut feeling that anything that truly changes behaviour will have to do so without the prospect of financial payback. By buying into the current assumptions about how the world should run, you&#8217;re maybe holding back the really ground-breaking ideas. There are some things that will work, sure, but thousands of ideas that could make the world better will never get off the ground because of a lack of business model.</p>
<p>What we need is a social-good model instead. We don&#8217;t need more space for entrepreneurs, but instead we need space for people who want to change the world for the better to do so. Not for money, but because it&#8217;s a good and noble and important thing to do. We need some way of supporting and developing great ideas that come out of events like the <a href="http://london.greenhackathon.com">London Green Hackathon</a>, even if they don&#8217;t have a way to make money for someone (though of course <a href="http://www.mastodonc.com">some do</a> and that&#8217;s great).</p>
<p>We need a Cleanweb R&amp;D Foundation of some kind, with a remit to simply make the world better and try things out. That would be a place that could really attack some truly innovative ideas. And it would be a hell of a lot of fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fixing the life support]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/01/05/fixing-the-life-support/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2012/01/05/fixing-the-life-support</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Somehow, this year feels different.</p>
<p>Maybe it&#8217;s because of the increase in public awareness of the problems with the world at the end of 2011. A greater understanding that governments and people don&#8217;t run the world any more, that we have given money too much power, that we are running full tilt at a cliff-edge; it feels like it&#8217;s adding up.</p>
<p>Charlie Brooker said recently that 2011&#160;<a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2011/dec/11/charlie-brooker-2011-season-finale">felt like a series finale</a>; I&#8217;m not sure about that, it felt to me more like the buildup in the penultimate episode. 2012 seems like the actual last episode when the big events will happen (probably with a few cliff-hangers left over for 2013).</p>
<p>This impending feeling that big events are coming could be imaginary of course, but I hope not. We <em>need</em> big events now (and I don&#8217;t mean the obvious 2012 fake-apocalypse fantasy). We are racing so fast towards collapse that we have to do something <em>now</em>, or we will be a cautionary tale in the Cockroach Book Of Ancient Civilisations. We still have the ability to save ourselves (just); I hope that this year brings the will to engage with the problem.</p>
<p>We need to grow up, realise the full-spectrum danger we are in, and do something about it. We need to <em>mature</em> as a species, and fast. We need to get over our selfish approach and make a better society for the future, together.</p>
<p>I am a software engineer; that makes me next to useless in a collapsed society. My daughter quite literally <em>needs</em> a functioning, liberal, caring society to keep her alive. Moving to a farmhouse, becoming self-sufficient and letting everyone else collapse is no good for me. A functioning technological society is an essential life support system.</p>
<p>With all that in mind, I am going into this year with an objective to make best use of the skills I have to attack the big problems where I can, and if it doesn&#8217;t work out, to fail magnificently having <em>done my best</em>. </p>
<p>I hope you&#8217;ll join me. We&#8217;ve got a hell of a job to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
