<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: election | James Smith]]></title>
  <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/categories/election/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-08T07:13:43+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://floppy.org.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Smith]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[james@floppy.org.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Face to Face]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/10/08/face-to-face/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-08T19:59:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/10/08/face-to-face</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the
<a href="/blog/categories/election/">election category</a> for other posts.</em></p>

<p>A few weeks ago, I held the <a href="/blog/2014/08/05/horsham-election-meetup-1/">first public meeting</a> for my election campaign.
It was a small affair, but it was clear that this was something that I&rsquo;m
going to have to do a lot more of. Whether it&rsquo;s creating an appointment
time for people to come and ask questions and put across concerns
individually, or a group discussion, it&rsquo;s good to get into a rhythm and
be available to people.</p>

<p>I decided I wanted to basically run a public meeting a week from the beginning of
October until the election. The idea is to provide a space for discussion, ideas,
questions, and for people to raise issues.</p>

<p>They will be poorly-attended at first, but the
message will spread, and starting is important. Question is, where to have
them? Well, as with everything else so far, let&rsquo;s look at the data!</p>

<h2>Wards</h2>

<p>Horsham constituency is divided into 18 wards. Just under half of them are
in Horsham itself, and the rest cover the surrounding countryside and
smaller towns. In order to be available to people, it would be good to run
at least one event in each ward, so that people don&rsquo;t have to travel too
far, and see their candidate in their local community.</p>

<p>However, wards vary widely in population, so it&rsquo;s not just a matter of
going to each one once. I should really go to the larger ones more, to try
and cover the population more evenly.</p>

<p><img src="/images/horsham_wards.png" alt="Wards" /></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/electionmaps">Ordnance Survey election map</a> shows wards as well as constituencies,
so it&rsquo;s easy enough to find which wards we need to cover. Each area has an
&ldquo;statistical identifier&rdquo;, which is a unique code for that area. Helpfully,
the ONS also break down their <a href="http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/data/area-first/">census statistics</a> using the same identifier,
so with a little bit of work, it&rsquo;s pretty easy to get the adult population of each
ward (16+ actually, but it was in 2011, so that&rsquo;s near enough).</p>

<table class='table table-striped'>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th> ID </th>
<th> Ward </th>
<th> Population </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007665 </td>
<td> Southwater </td>
<td> 7741</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007646 </td>
<td> Billingshurst and Shipley </td>
<td> 7403</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007657 </td>
<td> Horsham Park </td>
<td> 6502</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007678 </td>
<td> Crawley Down and Turners Hill </td>
<td> 5667</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007662 </td>
<td> Roffey South </td>
<td> 5237</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007661 </td>
<td> Roffey North </td>
<td> 5103</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007667 </td>
<td> Trafalgar </td>
<td> 4971</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007652 </td>
<td> Denne </td>
<td> 4788</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007656 </td>
<td> Holbrook West </td>
<td> 4606</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007668 </td>
<td> Ardingly and Balcombe </td>
<td> 4495</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007655 </td>
<td> Holbrook East </td>
<td> 4381</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007658 </td>
<td> Itchingfield, Slinfold and Warnham </td>
<td> 4335</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007677 </td>
<td> Copthorne and Worth </td>
<td> 4015</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007653 </td>
<td> Forest </td>
<td> 3021</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007648 </td>
<td> Broadbridge Heath </td>
<td> 2492</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007659 </td>
<td> Nuthurst </td>
<td> 2318</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007664 </td>
<td> Rusper and Colgate </td>
<td> 2137</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> E05007663 </td>
<td> Rudgwick </td>
<td> 2134</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>If we order the wards by population, and work out the number of weeks we
have available, we can work out which wards we have time to visit twice.
I&rsquo;ve left a gap around Christmas, and for a couple of other weeks
where I already know I&rsquo;m prebooked on the Tuesday (which is the day I&rsquo;m
aiming for).</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not as simple as just visiting in size order though; I&rsquo;ve manipulated
the list and swapped a few things around so that I jump around the constituency.
Ideally, every other week should be in Horsham, and the other weeks I&rsquo;ll
alternate east/west or north/south across the other wards. That should get
me near everyone on a fairly regular basis, and avoid spending too much
time concentrating on one area.</p>

<p>I did consider writing a bit of code to work this out, but as it was only
28 weeks and 18 locations, it wasn&rsquo;t worth it. Also, it might be a
variation of a very hard computer science problem, so no time for that.</p>

<p>As the dates turn out, I&rsquo;ll hit every ward in size order after the new year,
and I&rsquo;m starting with events in the largest 10 between now and Christmas. Another
nice thing is that the largest ward is Horsham Park, right in the middle of town,
so in the week of the election hopefully we can get a nice big finish!</p>

<h2>Venues</h2>

<p>So, where to actually meet people? I had heard that some public buildings
are available for political candidates to use for free, so I called the
local council&rsquo;s election officer to have a chat. As with my other
conversations with election folk at various organisations, they were very
helpful.</p>

<p>The rule seems to be that candidates can use a publicly-maintained building
free of charge; however, many things like village halls, etc, are not in fact
publicly maintained buildings. In fact the only places they could suggest that
were widely spread across the area were schools, who apparently would be OK
with being used in that way. There shouldn&rsquo;t be a hire charge, but they might
have to charge for caretaking; having someone to lock up, etc.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not that simple either; there are more rooms available free of charge, but only
once the election has actually been called, which basically means during April.</p>

<p>So, I&rsquo;m just going to have to call a whole load of places and see
what I can negotiate on a case-by-case basis. It will end up adding a fair amount
to the budget too &ndash; if it costs me £30 a week for a room, times 28 weeks&hellip; erk.</p>

<p>But, it&rsquo;s important, so it&rsquo;s time to put my money where my mouth is.</p>

<h2>Let&rsquo;s Go!</h2>

<p>So, armed with that information and a plan, I&rsquo;ve started booking things, and I actually ran
the first event in the series last night in Roffey North. Keep an eye on the <a href="http://horsham.somethingnew.org.uk/calendar">calendar</a> for future events, and I&rsquo;ll add them as I get the venues booked in, and if you&rsquo;re in Horsham, hopefully I&rsquo;ll see you soon at an event near you!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Democracy geeks at EMFCamp 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/08/31/democracy-geeks-at-emfcamp-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-31T19:22:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/08/31/democracy-geeks-at-emfcamp-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the <a href="/blog/categories/election/">election category</a> for other posts.</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m on the train on the way home from <a href="http://emfcamp.org">Electromagnetic Field 2014</a>. It&rsquo;s a sort of technology / maker festival in a field near Milton Keynes. Imagine a load of tech geeks camping in tents with laser cutters, LEDs, laptops, excellent wifi, and a robot that makes cocktails. It&rsquo;s an amazing place.</p>

<p>I was lucky enough to get a speaking slot to talk about my current project, standing for Parliament next year. As it happened, there were two other talks on a similar theme; <a href="https://twitter.com/tom_watson">Tom Watson MP</a> spoke about <a href="/blog/2014/07/14/drip-an-open-letter-to-francis-maude/">DRIP</a>, and <a href="http://www.danjellinek.com/">Dan Jellinek</a> talked about digital democracy ideas and tools, so there was a common thread between all our talks.</p>

<p>All three of us wanted more people to get engaged in politics. Tom Watson went as far as challenging people to join their local Labour or Conservative parties and change them from the inside (which, given enough people, could totally work, though I would like to try a different path).</p>

<p>My talk went down really well, I think. I was very pleased with the turnout, and there were loads of great questions at the end. I came away more convinced that what I&rsquo;m trying to do will resonate with a whole load of people. The new party name that I presented also went down really well, though I&rsquo;ll tell <em>you</em> all about it in a future post &ndash; stay tuned.</p>

<p><img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BwTPxI5IIAAkHoe.jpg" alt="EMFcamp talk" /></p>

<p>To give people a chance to discuss things further, we held an informal democracy meetup on Saturday evening. I expected a few people to turn up, but we had over 40 and packed out our tent, with standing room only. What followed was two hours of lively debate, discussion, and passion from the people who came along, and I was absolutely blown away by how much people <em>do</em> care, and <em>do</em> want to get involved.</p>

<p>The icing on the cake was Sunday morning. I was walking to get some breakfast and I ran into one of the participants from the night before. He told me that I&rsquo;d inspired him to stand as well, which is just <em>amazing</em>. I&rsquo;ve since had a few others email or grab me around the event saying they want to get more involved and help out somehow. I&rsquo;m &hellip; honoured.</p>

<p>After this weekend, I&rsquo;m even more convinced that this is the start of a movement, the start of something big. The start of something new.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaflet Drops]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/08/13/leaflet-drops/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-13T16:50:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/08/13/leaflet-drops</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the <a href="/blog/categories/election/">election category</a> for other posts.</em></p>

<p>This morning, I learnt a bit about leafletting. As a candidate, the bare minimum for a campaign has to be getting a leaflet through every door, so that people are informed of their choices (although a good half the candidates at the 2010 election didn&rsquo;t manage that).</p>

<p>I figured this would be a major cost; I&rsquo;m amazed how wrong that turned out to be.</p>

<h2>Printing</h2>

<p>First things first &ndash; how much will it cost to get these things printed? Ideally I&rsquo;d like to have a 4-page A5 leaflet with full colour printing, and enough for every household in the constituency.</p>

<p>How many is that? Well, let&rsquo;s start with a rough estimate from the 2011 census. The <a href="http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/data/area-first/">ONS data explorer</a> makes this pretty easy. You can choose your reporting area by parliamentary constituency, and then find out all sorts of information about the area, including number of households. Turns out, in 2011, there were 43,380 households in the Horsham constituency.</p>

<p>So what will it cost us to print that many? Last night I emailed a request for quotes to four local printers, and was amazed to get back quotes in the £1000-1500 range. Considering that party spending on unsolicited mailings was around £4500 at the last election, this is a lot less than I expected. I wonder where the rest of their money went? Presumably more than one leaflet; perhaps targeted drops for likely voters.</p>

<h2>Delivery</h2>

<p>This is where it gets awesome. As a parliamentary candidate, you get one free mailing from the Royal Mail. That&rsquo;s right, <em>free</em>.</p>

<p>You can choose addressed mailings to every voter, or an unaddressed mailing to each household (i.e. a normal leaflet drop). The Royal Mail have <a href="http://www.royalmail.com/specialist-services/candidate-mailing">a special candidate mailing area on their website</a> all about this, and so I had a read and phoned up their election people, who were <em>very</em> helpful.</p>

<p>The way it works is; a few weeks before the election, you send your artwork to them to check for compliance with the election and postal rules, and once it&rsquo;s approved, you get given a named Election Manager and instructions on where to drop off your leaflets. Simple as that. They also tell you exactly how many you need to print.</p>

<p>After that, you just get them printed, and drop them off at least 7-10 days before the election. They then deliver them over the next week. You can deliver earlier of course, that&rsquo;s just the latest possible date.</p>

<p>They were helpful enough to tell me how many leaflets were dropped in the recent EU elections, which was about 47,300. A bit higher than the census data, but not far off. I&rsquo;d better budget for about 50,000 next year, allowing for new development, etc, but that won&rsquo;t change the figures too much.</p>

<p>They have a <a href="http://www.royalmail.com/sites/default/files/CandidateMail_EuropeanElection_Brochure_Mar2014a.pdf">guidance document for the EU elections</a> up on their site. For now, it&rsquo;s good enough to work from; the 2015 election guidance won&rsquo;t be up until next year.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>So, all in all this looks pretty easy. If I can raise £1500-ish, and design a leaflet (which some of the printers can help with for a little more), I can get the Royal Mail to deliver it, and everyone in the area will get told about me.</p>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t all the printing of course; more will be needed to be able to hand out flyers to people before the final leaflet drop, but it&rsquo;s a great baseline. I thought that would cost a lot more, and it&rsquo;s once again underlined just how accessible this actually is.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Political Cartography]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/08/07/political-cartography/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-07T20:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/08/07/political-cartography</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the <a href="/blog/categories/election/">election category</a> for other posts.</em></p>

<p>One thing you really need to know when standing as a candidate is what areas are actually part of your constituency. Constituencies are pretty weird shapes, especially out in the country, and the area is probably larger than you think. So, time to find out for sure.</p>

<p>Fortunately the Ordnance Survey makes this easy. Their <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/election-maps/gb/">Election Maps</a> service shows all the constituency, ward, and other boundaries you might want in a nice map format. Enter your constituency name in the box, choose the right one, and you get something like this (apologies for the screenshot, there&rsquo;s no way to embed):</p>

<p><img src="/images/horsham_constituency.png" alt="Horsham constituency OS map" /></p>

<p>Now, what I really want is a map on my wall that I can refer to easily. The Election Maps service does have a print option, but it&rsquo;s just to print a single page yourself, and no way is that good enough for what I want.</p>

<p>Fortunately, OS come to the rescue again with their <a href="https://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/shop/custom-made-maps.html">custom map printing</a>. Unfortunately, there&rsquo;s no link on the election maps to &ldquo;order a custom map of this area&rdquo; (which would be awesome, OS, if you&rsquo;re listening) so we have to do it manually.</p>

<p>In my case, I found a point roughly in the middle of the constituency&rsquo;s bounding box, Lower Beeding, and I found that at Landranger scale (1:50000), the whole constituency would fit on one map. This probably won&rsquo;t always be the case, but it worked for me. £16.99 and 5 days later, and I have an 80x80cm wall map of my constituency is hanging on my wall:</p>

<p><img src="/images/wall_map.jpg" alt="Horsham constituency wall map" /></p>

<p>Unfortunately, that custom map doesn&rsquo;t include the boundary of the constituency, so I had to draw it on with a highlighter pen, but it&rsquo;s not a bad solution.</p>

<p>Note: I tried to do this using OpenStreetMap, but I just couldn&rsquo;t work out how. If anyone knows, then please tell me, I&rsquo;d love to have a method of using the open data in OSM to plan my campaigning :)</p>

<p>Another note: Election boundaries are STUPID. Whoever decided some of those shapes&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Horsham Election Meetup #1]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/08/05/horsham-election-meetup-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-05T23:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/08/05/horsham-election-meetup-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the <a href="/blog/categories/election/">election category</a> for other posts.</em></p>

<p>Last night was our first Horsham election meetup, and while very useful, it&rsquo;s left so many thoughts swirling around my brain that it&rsquo;s hard to get them in any kind of order. These, I think, were the main outcomes for me:</p>

<h2>Independent movement</h2>

<p>There is a growing movement of independent candidates across Horsham, with myself at national level, and a number of others at district level. With all the seats up for election at the same time next year, there&rsquo;s a lot of possible cooperation to be had. There is a general disillusionment with our representatives at all levels, that they are not representing the concerns of residents, which plays into the hands of independents.</p>

<p>However, a danger here is that if there is a movement of independent local councillor candidates, that I get drawn into that <em>too far</em>, and don&rsquo;t get enough focus on the specific needs of the MP campaign. This is dangerous, not least because Horsham district and constituency are not the same shape; some of my constituents are in Mid Sussex District, and not all Horsham District residents vote in Horsham constituency.</p>

<p>But, it will be helpful to have allies; we&rsquo;ve set up a mailing list for independents in the Horsham area &ndash; if you want to join, visit the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/horsham-unparty">Horsham Unparty google group</a>.</p>

<h2>Issues</h2>

<p>We discussed the most important issues to Horsham right now, and I&rsquo;m glad to say that they were pretty much in line with my expectations. Gatwick expansion is a biggie, but the main concern at the moment seems to be around the planning and development going on around the town. Housing needs to be built, but it&rsquo;s not being built in a way that local people are happy with. They feel that their views are ignored, and that decisions are being taken behind closed doors.</p>

<p>Both these play nicely into my national stance on greater transparency at all levels, environmental issues around airports and vehicles, and fixing the democratic process. It&rsquo;ll be important in the campaign to keep my focus on the national-level trends and laws that make local problems worse, while trying to facilitate solutions to local problems. The advantage of having a group of independent candidates for the council is that we can have good coverage of whatever level is actually responsible for an issue.</p>

<p>My action from this is to start creating a set of local issue pages on <a href="http://openhorsham.org.uk">openhorsham.org.uk</a> and set out my views and how they link to national legislation, etc.</p>

<h2>Campaign planning</h2>

<p>We discussed how to engage with people during the campaign. We threw around ideas of town centre engagement on a Saturday morning, and running local surgeries around the constituency. We talked about engaging with influential local groups (and being explicit about getting endorsements!), and also about increasing the number of election hustings meetings &ndash; last time round, there were two, both run by church groups. We need to improve that this time.</p>

<p>We also talked about getting a team together to help. Volunteers for leaflet dropping are essential, but it&rsquo;s becoming increasingly clear to me that I need other people involved on my campaign to help run and organise it. How to find all these people? I&rsquo;m not sure.</p>

<h2>Media</h2>

<p>Engagement with local media is important. I need to be writing opinion pieces and letters on a regular basis. I have no problem with writing (I don&rsquo;t think), but my instinct is always to publish immediately online; I will have to restrain myself slightly to get anything visible in the local paper.</p>

<h2>Too Much Information</h2>

<p>There is always a danger that as a new entrant into the democratic arena, there are many many people out there who know a lot more than you about the area, the process, and the politics. These people are <em>great</em>, but they do leave your head spinning. It&rsquo;s important to take what is useful on board, but not allow yourself to be subsumed into the stream of information.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, to be a genuine candidate, I have to be <em>myself</em>, and not try to turn myself into an expert politician. So far, while there are massive gaps in my knowledge, my instincts have been confirmed, so I feel like I&rsquo;m on the right track.</p>

<p>It will be an interesting year. Balancing the different aspects will be hard, but I need to make sure I remain focused on representing what the constituents want from their MP, and making sure they understand what I have to offer. <em>Everything</em> else is negotiable.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
