<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: depression | James Smith]]></title>
  <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/categories/depression/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-01T22:23:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://floppy.org.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Smith]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[james@floppy.org.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Depression Is A Bug, Not A Feature]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/10/10/depression-is-a-bug-not-a-feature/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-10T11:02:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/10/10/depression-is-a-bug-not-a-feature</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is apparently <a href="http://www.mentalhealth.org.uk/our-work/world-mental-health-day/">World Mental Health Day</a>, which makes it an appropriate time to talk a little about depression. I was thinking of doing this anyway, but today seems a good day to do it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve suffered from intermittent depression for the last few years. If I&rsquo;ve been quiet on Twitter or GitHub for the last couple of weeks, it&rsquo;s because I&rsquo;m currently recovering from my fourth round; they seem to come on just under every two years, it seems. It&rsquo;s not a pleasant thing to admit to, but I honestly believe that only by talking about our experiences can we normalise this, and when you&rsquo;re in the grip of depression, what you really need is to know that you are <em>not alone</em>.</p>

<p>The first time round, I didn&rsquo;t really understand what was happening. Work was stressful, but not ridiculously so, but I lost the ability to cope with it. I couldn&rsquo;t make decisions, and I remember times when I would have to run away and actually <em>hide in a darkened room</em> for a while when something tricky came up like, I dunno, triaging the Monday morning bug list. Fortunately I worked for a flight simulation company at the time, so dark rooms were in plentiful supply.</p>

<p>Depression, for someone who works entirely in their mind, as we do as creative programmers, is utterly debilitating. Imagine:</p>

<ul>
<li>Your mind slows down</li>
<li>You lose the ability to focus, or think straight about problems</li>
<li>You lose the ability to make decisions; even deciding on lunch can be impossible</li>
<li>You lose confidence; feel like you&rsquo;re a fraud, and that you&rsquo;ll be found out</li>
<li>You lose the big picture; you can&rsquo;t hold it all in your head</li>
<li>Anxiety builds, and eventually you find yourself hiding in darkened rooms trying not to panic (and often failing)</li>
</ul>


<p>Our jobs depend on those exact qualities, and often, for many of us, so does our self-worth. I try to compare it to being a sportsman and having a broken leg; it&rsquo;s take you out of the game just as surely, and it robs you of your reason for being just as much.</p>

<p>However; it is manageable. I&rsquo;m still learning, but I am getting better at it. I&rsquo;m spotting it earlier each time, am getting better at warning my co-workers, and have no qualms now with going to the doctor and getting the help I need once it becomes clear. I&rsquo;ve had <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citalopram">medication</a> the last three times; I&rsquo;m currently a week and a half in to this round.</p>

<p>The important thing to realise that <em>it&rsquo;s not a failing, it&rsquo;s an illness</em>. Your brain is a big bag of chemicals that govern your emotions; there&rsquo;s no magical soul hiding there, I&rsquo;m afraid. But sometimes those chemicals go wrong. In the case of depression, it&rsquo;s apparently a long-term reduction in the amount of Serotonin in the brain that does it. Your synapses hoover up too much, so there&rsquo;s not enough left in the gaps to conduct the signals effectively. It can be brought on by stress, by exhaustion, by sudden shocks, or even by a more &lsquo;normal&rsquo; illness. The brain gets out of kilter, and then just gets <em>stuck</em> in this cycle.</p>

<p>But, as an engineer, <em>I can relate to this</em>. Depression is a <em>bug</em>, not a failure on <em>my</em> part. The medication prevents this serotonin reuptake, and lets your brain recover, and remember how to balance itself. I&rsquo;ve proved this to myself time and again; a few days into the medication, I&rsquo;m <em>back</em>. I&rsquo;m me again. For example, I couldn&rsquo;t have written this two days ago, but today I&rsquo;m feeling more&hellip; <em>present</em>. I&rsquo;m not there yet, but it won&rsquo;t be long now.</p>

<p>The people around you have a huge part to play. You need their understanding, support, and for them to give you time to recover. I wouldn&rsquo;t have been able to cope with this if not for my family, my colleagues at <a href="http://amee.com">AMEE</a> and the <a href="http://www.theodi.org">ODI</a>, and for a great friend of mine who, many years ago, taught me how depression works <em>before</em> I found out for myself.</p>

<p>There are a few links I&rsquo;d recommend reading about this:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://revdancatt.com/2012/07/26/leaving-the-guardian-creativity-vs-mild-depression-the-quantified-self-and-running/">Leaving the Guardian, Creativity vs Mild Depression</a> by Rev Dan Catt</li>
<li><a href="http://hyperboleandahalf.blogspot.co.uk/2011/10/adventures-in-depression.html">Adventures in Depression</a> and <a href="http://hyperboleandahalf.blogspot.co.uk/2013/05/depression-part-two.html">Part 2</a> by Hyperbole and a Half</li>
</ul>


<p>That was a bit long, but the TL;DR is this: If you&rsquo;re feeling the symptoms above, then talk to your doctor and <em>get help</em>. It&rsquo;s just a bug, it&rsquo;s fixable, and you are <em>not</em> a failure. If you know someone who seems to be suffering, then try to help them understand what&rsquo;s happening, don&rsquo;t just tell them to &ldquo;cheer up&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
