<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: democracy | James Smith]]></title>
  <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/categories/democracy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-06T08:46:42+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://floppy.org.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Smith]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[james@floppy.org.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DRIP: An Open Letter to Francis Maude]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/14/drip-an-open-letter-to-francis-maude/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T10:16:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/07/14/drip-an-open-letter-to-francis-maude</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear Mr Maude,</p>

<p>I am writing to you today as one of your constituents, in relation to the imminent vote on the Data Retention and Investigatory Powers Bill. The government&rsquo;s actions in this area give me great cause for concern.</p>

<p>In April, the EU Data Retention Directive was ruled as a breach of basic citizen rights by the European Courts of Justice. Too much data stored for too long, on too many people. Then, suddenly, last week, the DRIP Bill appears, ready to be pushed through with haste, due to an &ldquo;emergency&rdquo; need to respond to this.</p>

<p>Firstly, what has changed since April? What requires upsetting the normal procedures of review and taking time over legislation? Civic society will not have sufficient time to inspect this legislation and object (though many are trying their best to analyse the text before it becomes law). How is there a sudden &ldquo;emergency&rdquo;?</p>

<p>Secondly, you are a champion of transparency and accountability within government. How does the drafting of legislation in secret, even <em>with</em> cross-party consensus, square with that? Are citizens not to be trusted on matters such as this? I will be interested in seeing your vote on this, to see how far your commitment to transparency goes.</p>

<p>Thirdly, the bill itself gives much cause for concern. The initial claim was that it only reinstates existing powers (which, by the way, were declared illegal), but <a href="http://cyberleagle.blogspot.com/2014/07/dissecting-emergency-data-retention-and.html">analysis is suggesting</a> that it also extends that power to many other areas.</p>

<p>We are a democracy. We are a free country. Secretive extension of the surveillance state, done in haste without oversight, <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/debate/article-2690181/David-Davis-devastating-attack-loss-privacy-This-data-law-catching-terrorists-lust-power.html">has no place here</a>. The government has a responsibility to balance the needs of security services against the freedoms of its citizens, which were hard-won over hundreds of years, and should not be limited lightly.</p>

<p>I announced a couple of weeks ago that <a href="/blog/2014/06/27/standing-for-parliament-in-2015/">I intend to stand for Horsham in next year&rsquo;s general election</a>, on a <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk">collaborative and open-source political platform</a> built by normal citizens.</p>

<p>Horsham is my home, so my choice to stand was not <em>against you</em>, but rather <em>for Horsham</em>. However, with the government&rsquo;s actions over this bill, I am rather looking forward to challenging your choices and true commitment to openness and transparency over the next year.</p>

<p>Note: I have published this letter on my <a href="http://floppy.org.uk">personal website</a>, and will also publish your response to it, to give you proper right of reply.</p>

<p>Yours sincerely,
James Smith</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Standing for Parliament in 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/06/27/standing-for-parliament-in-2015/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-27T10:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/06/27/standing-for-parliament-in-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is part of my series about standing as an MP. See the <a href="/blog/categories/election/">election category</a> for other posts.</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve got an exciting announcement to make; <strong>in May 2015, I&rsquo;m planning to stand in the
general election to be MP for Horsham</strong>. I&rsquo;ll be running on the
principles in the <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk">OpenPolitics Manifesto</a>,
an open source collaborative manifesto that <em>anyone</em> can contribute to; I&rsquo;m reasonably sure that&rsquo;s a world first.</p>

<h2>Why do this?</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m an optimist. I look to the future and hope that we can build a brighter, happier, more collaborative, more equal society for everyone, enabled by the best aspects of our technology. I see a future where we can do <em>democracy itself</em> better, where we all have a say in the way we do things together. I realise that&rsquo;s utopian, but I figure that it&rsquo;s better to have a idea of where you want to get to than just stumbling from crisis to crisis without an end goal in mind.</p>

<p>On the other hand, I&rsquo;ve come to the conclusion over the last few years that nobody is
representing me or others who are optimistically working towards a better future. I&rsquo;m fed up of the politics of fear, the <a href="https://therearenoothers.wordpress.com/2011/12/28/othering-101-what-is-othering/">othering</a> of the vulnerable, and the misguided doctrine of austerity. I&rsquo;m also frustrated by our lack of sufficient climate action, and our dismal record when adopting supposedly &ldquo;new&rdquo; technologies like the web. The bleak future offered by the current political choices just isn&rsquo;t a place I want to be.</p>

<p>So, I think we can do better, and the right way to deal with that in our current system is <em>provide the option yourself</em> and stand for office.</p>

<h2>Starting something</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m the first to admit that it will be a hard fight; I&rsquo;m standing in a very safe Conservative seat, against Francis Maude, a cabinet minister. However, Horsham is where I live, and so while there are probably easier targets, this one falls to me, and I&rsquo;m ready to take it on.</p>

<p>Also, this isn&rsquo;t simply about winning one seat next May; it&rsquo;s about trying to inspire others to stand across the country on the same platform, and about getting started on the long haul of building a political movement across many years and multiple elections. There is a growing movement towards a more networked citizen-powered form of democracy across the world, and standing on an open-source manifesto is an exciting way to be part of that.</p>

<h2>Let&rsquo;s do it</h2>

<p>In summary; I&rsquo;m not a politician, but I <em>do</em> think things need to change if we&rsquo;re going to build a decent future. If you agree, and like me you can&rsquo;t trust anyone else to fix things for you, stand where <em>you</em> are, and maybe we&rsquo;ll put a party name on this thing.</p>

<p><strong>Let&rsquo;s bring an Open Revolution to British politics.</strong></p>

<p><em>If you&rsquo;re in the Horsham area, visit <a href="http://openhorsham.org.uk">openhorsham.org.uk</a> to keep in touch with the campaign when it starts.</em></p>

<p><em>To get involved in writing the manifesto, visit <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk">openpolitics.org.uk</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/OpenPoliticsUK">@OpenPoliticsUK</a> on Twitter.</em></p>

<p><em>And finally, you can follow me on Twitter at <a href="http://twitter.com/Floppy">@Floppy</a>. If you want to stand where you are, let me know!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Open Democracy Stack]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/01/25/the-open-democracy-stack/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-25T08:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2014/01/25/the-open-democracy-stack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I wrote my blog post <a href="/blog/2013/07/05/its-time-to-step-up/">&ldquo;It&rsquo;s time to step up&rdquo;</a> last summer, I&rsquo;ve got very interested in the concept of Open Democracy, and have been discovering a lot about what&rsquo;s currently going on in this area. This post is an attempt to delineate the various efforts, mainly for my own benefit, but perhaps others may find it useful as well.</p>

<p>There are a number of overlapping concepts. First, we have political parties, with their manifestos. Then we have the idea of a constitution, and finally the policy-making process itself. A few examples:</p>

<h2>Party Manifestos</h2>

<p>Firstly, and most familiar, we have the political party manifesto. My view is that this is a collection of statements that outlines the beliefs of the party, and how it intends to attack problems. It isn&rsquo;t necessarily detailed, or fully costed, but is indicative of the direction that the party wishes to go. The Pirate Party UK will soon be launching their next open manifesto process, and I&rsquo;m experimenting with building a new political platform under the <a href="http://openpolitics.org.uk/manifesto">OpenPolitics Manifesto</a> project (an interesting aspect of which is that is designed to deprecate the party system).</p>

<h2>Constitutions</h2>

<p>Then, we have the idea of a constitution. The UK does not have a proper written constitution, but there is a crowdsourcing effort going on at <a href="http://www.constitutionuk.com/">Constitution UK</a> to create one. Interestingly, a lot of ideas that are going into that are ones that I consider far too specific for a constitution, and instead belong in a party manifesto. A consititution should be short, simple, and consist of the basic rules on which we all agree. The constitution can be added to, but it&rsquo;s best to start with something very simple.</p>

<p>Some examples; the structure of Parliament, the role (or lack thereof) of the monarchy, and the <a href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/udhr/">UDHR</a> would belong in a constitution, but things like economic and social policy, including the role of the NHS and welfare state, would not.</p>

<h2>Tenuous Analogies</h2>

<p>To use a computer analogy, if a party manifesto can be considered a piece of software, which the user can choose to run or not, a consitution is more like the OS; a lower-level design that allows the higher-level manifesto to run, and on which all participants in the system agree.</p>

<p>(Obviously, there are many OSes. And we have many countries with different constitutions, so I&rsquo;m sticking with this analogy for now&hellip; let&rsquo;s see where it breaks)</p>

<h2>Open Policy</h2>

<p>Then we have the policy-design level, which is I think what the <a href="http://my.civilservice.gov.uk/policy/">Cabinet Office Open Policy Team</a> is looking at. This is apolitical, driven by the choices made by the electorate, and is about effective implementation of the ideas in a manifesto. In my mind this is like the content that you create using a piece of software. So, it reflects the manifesto commitment used to drive it, but then is richer in terms of how that commitment is implemented, funded, and so on.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The world of Open Democeacy is one with many pieces, and how they all fit together isn&rsquo;t necessarily obvious at the first look. Anyone who wants to contribute to this (including myself) should understand the &lsquo;stack&rsquo; to know which ideas fit where.</p>

<p>And of course, all this could be wrong, it&rsquo;s just my assessment of it. If anyone wants to enlighten me further, please do, and please contribute to all the open democracy efforts that are out there, at whatever level you feel is most appropriate for you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It's Time To Step Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/07/05/its-time-to-step-up/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-05T20:08:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2013/07/05/its-time-to-step-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I find the current state of politics in the UK incredibly depressing.</p>

<p>Unsurprisingly, I find myself disagreeing with most of what the Conservative party is doing in government, and in particular with the narrative they are using to justify it. The Liberal Democrats may claim they have moderated the worst excesses of the Conservatives, but have still allowed the near-privatisation of the NHS, and failed utterly to do anything with the concessions they got in the coalition agreement on things like electoral reform.</p>

<p>On the opposition side&hellip; well, what opposition? I personally like Ed, but it&rsquo;s obvious the media have their teeth into him and will never let him have a proper voice. Worst of all, the Labour Party are buying into the aforementioned narrative of &ldquo;this is what needs to be done&rdquo;. They don&rsquo;t challenge the demonisation of the poor, while entrenched power runs off with the money that&rsquo;s being stripped from our welfare state.</p>

<p>Protest votes are heading to the charismatic far right, with the Old Tory caricatures that are UKIP grabbing all the headlines and dragging the entire country down a path that we <em>really</em> shouldn&rsquo;t be considering. The other minor parties are next to useless. The Greens, really the party I agree with most, will always be mired in 1970&rsquo;s style environmentalism, which nobody will ever vote for en masse.</p>

<p>All this adds up to an uncomfortable truth. Nobody in the public sphere in this country is speaking for <em>me</em>. The narrative is about how the past was better, and the present is broken. The people in power seem to lust after the old days of empire, rather than working out how to take us into a bright shiny future.</p>

<p>The problem is; the future isn&rsquo;t stopping. It will change <em>every single institution we have</em>, and we should be getting excited about that fact and making sure it works <em>for</em> us. That&rsquo;s what I dedicate my life to, to making sure the future is a <em>better</em> place for <em>everyone</em>, but nobody in power seems to want to take us there.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="/blog/2009/11/10/the-activist-geek-philosophy">written before</a> about a kind of shared philosophy amongst the open society community, but I stopped short of some of the more controversial areas of politics. I think it&rsquo;s time for us to stop doing that. There is an unspoken tradition in our community of trying to be beyond political statements, to fix things from the outside, but the way GDS are reforming the civil service (which I <em>will</em> give the Conservatives credit for, or at least <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Maude">some of them</a>) has reminded me that in order to truly change the system, you sometimes have to <em>become</em> the system.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a general election coming in a couple of years. Those of us who are looking to the future should have our hands in the game. It&rsquo;s time for our community to grow up, take responsibility, and stop leaving the debate to the relics. We have the tools and the skills to do this, and a lot of allies. We&rsquo;re already changing the world from behind the scenes; it&rsquo;s time to start leading from the front as well.</p>

<p>If someone is already doing something about this, I want to know who. If not, we should get started by setting up a GitHub repository, and get collaborating on policy for a brighter future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Francis Maude on the LRRA]]></title>
    <link href="http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2010/11/26/francis-maude-on-the-lrra/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://floppy.org.uk/blog/2010/11/26/francis-maude-on-the-lrra</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
In 2006, I wrote to my MP about the Legislative and Regulator Reform Bill (now Act). The bill contained extremely dangerous powers for Ministers to change anything they liked, giving them the ability to get away with pretty much anything without a proper vote. I campaigned against it, with many others, through <a href="http://saveparliament.org.uk">Save Parliament</a>.
</p>




<p>
Anyway, my MP happens to be Francis Maude, who is now Minister for the Cabinet Office. It turns out that his government is now advancing a bill with similar powers, the <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/law/afua-hirsch-law-blog/2010/nov/09/lords-quangos">Public Bodies Bill</a>. Now, I admit I&#8217;ve not had chance to follow this in detail, so I <b>don&#8217;t</b> know if it&#8217;s as bad, or if it&#8217;s more limited. However, others who know more might be interested to know what Francis Maude had to say about those sort of powers four years ago.
</p>




<blockquote>
&#8220;I am particularly concerned at the potential for Parliament to be bypassed by the order-making powers contained in Part 1 of the Billl. These powers are extremely constitutionally significant."
</blockquote>




<blockquote>
&#8220;It is imperative that the circumstances in which these powers can be used are limited and clearly set out in the Bill."
</blockquote>




<p>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/r-j-smith/sets/72157625471474192/detail/">The full scans</a> are available on my Flickr stream, for anyone who is interested.
</p>




<p style="text-align:center">
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/r-j-smith/5208470529/in/set-72157625471474192/"><img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4107/5208470529_56cec99d52_m.jpg"/></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/r-j-smith/5208441831/in/set-72157625471474192/"><img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4132/5208441831_2d53fcd63e_m.jpg"/></a>
</p>




<p>
Maybe the PBB is consistent with what he said 4 years ago, but maybe not. I&#8217;d be interested to know.
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
